Finding Aid for Law School (University of Michigan), 1852-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Student Activities and Organizations, 1894-1996; 4 linear feet
  The Student Activities and Organizations series is comprised of Dean's Office files relating to student activities and organizations and the records of several organizations. The series is divided into several subseries which, in-part, reflect the various accessions in which materials were received. Pre-1985 Accessions, (2 linear feet, 1894-1987 boxes 63-64)] include case club and practice court records, 1894-1971; papers concerning the Henry M. Campbell Moot Court Competition, 1961-1974; course and student listings, 1897-1901; thesis topics, 1898-1900; and a volume of Tau Epsilon Rho fraternity records, 1939-1962. Also of note is a 1987 report on minority students covering the period from the 1920s to 1987. The Campbell Competition records include perfunctory correspondence with several US Supreme Court justices inviting them to serve as judges for the moot court proceedings. Some additional records relating to these topics are located in more recently received accessions.
  The Student Organizations subseries [1999 Accession, boxes 116-117] contains the deans' files on various student groups and projects. Of particular interest may be the Black Action Movement files, which contain resolutions, memoranda and correspondence reflecting the law faculty's reactions to the BAM strike and other activities; a continuation of the Campbell Competition files from previous accessions; and the Student Senate files, which include meeting minutes and correspondence with the deans.
  - Courses
    - Record of Courses with Graduate and Special Students, 1897/98-1900/01 (Box 63)
  - Case Club/Practice Court Records
    - Practice Court Records, 1894-1901; 1 volumes (Box 63)
    - Cases and Notes, 1894-1908; 4 volumes (Box 63)
    - Record Book, 1925-1951 (Volume Bimu C61)
    - Financial Records, 1946-1971 (Box 63)
  - Student Activities
    - Henry M. Campbell Moot Court Competition, 1961-1974; 7 folders (Box 64)
    - Minority Student Report (1920s-1987), 2 volumes (Box 64)
    - Student Theses, 1898-1900; 3 volumes (Box 64)
    - Tau Epsilon Rho, 1939-1962 (Box 64)
    - Student Senate Minutes, 1982-1985 (Box 64)
  - Student Organizations
    - American Indian Law Student Association, 1983 (Box 116)
    - Asian Americans, 1975 (Box 116)
    - Barristers, 1966-1987 (Box 116)
    - Black Action Movement (BAM) (Law School resolutions, memoranda, and correspondence), 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 116)
    - Black Law Alumni Society, 1977-1980 (Box 116)
    - Black Law Student Alliance, 1968-1993; 2 folders
    - Campbell Competition
      - 1975 (Box 116)
        (includes student briefs)
      - 1976 (Box 116)
      - 1977 (Box 116)
      - 1978, 2 folders (Box 116)
      - 1979-1984 (Box 116)
      - 1985-1994 (Box 116)
      - General, 1974-1984 (Box 116)
    - Case Clubs, 1972-1974 (Box 116)
    - Civil Liberties Volunteers, 1980 (Box 116)
    - Civil Rights Research Council, 1968 (Box 116)
    - Delta Theta Phi, 1986 (Box 116)
    - Environmental Law Society, 1974-1992 (Box 116)
    - Family Law Project, 1987 (Box 116)
    - Federalist Society, 1986-1989 (Box 116)
    - Feminist Legal Services, 1977-1979 (Box 116)
    - Grievance Committee, 1977 (Box 116)
    - Hispanic Law Students Association (formerly La Raza), 1975-1990 (Box 116)
    - International Law Society, 1964-1986 (Box 117)
    - Jewish Law Students Association, 1983-1987 (Box 117)
    - Law Spouses Association (formerly Student Law Wives), 1967; 1975 (Box 117)
    - Lawyers Guild, 1969-1996 (Box 117)
    - Legal Aid Clinic (Washtenaw County Legal Aid Society), 1964-1979 (Box 117)
    - Rainbow Law Students Alliance, 1990-1996 (Box 117)
      (formerly Queer Law Students Alliance, formerly Lesbian and Gay Law Students)
    - Inmate Assistance Program, 1968-1974 (Box 117)
      (formerly Milan Prison Program)
    - National Black American Law Students Association, 1971 (Box 117)
    - National Moot Court, 1967-1978 (Box 117)
    - Phi Alpha Delta, 1976-1986 (Box 117)
    - Public Interest Law Cooperative, 1980 (Box 117)
    - Res Gestae, 1968-1996 (Box 117)
    - Speakers Program--Lawyers Club, 1962-1971 (Box 117)
    - Student Funded Fellowship, 1979-1994 (Box 117)
    - Student Senate
      - 1971-1994, 4 folders (Box 117)
      - Bylaws, 1972-1976; undated (Box 117)
      - Minutes, 1971-1975 (Box 117)
    - Women Law Students Organization, 1973-1985 (Box 117)
- Law Quadrangle and William W. Cook, 1919-1938
  The Law Quadrangle and William W. Cook, 1919-1938 [Pre-1985 Accessions] series (3 linear feet), contains papers concerning the construction and management of the Law Quadrangle: the Lawyers' Club Building, the Legal Research Building, the John P. Cook Dormitory and Hutchins Hall. The series also contains some papers of William W. Cook, law school alumnus and donor of the funding to build the Law Quadrangle.
  - Law Quadrangle Buildings
    - Design and Construction
      The subseries relating to the design and construction of the buildings includes chronological correspondence, in reverse order, between the parties involved in the construction: the architectural firm of York and Sawyer, subcontractors, the law school administration, University of Michigan administration, and William W. Cook. The subseries also contains topical correspondence specifically related to the two major construction projects: the Lawyers' Club building and Hutchins Hall. This correspondence was originally arranged topically and that arrangement was preserved. The subseries also includes the budgets and contracts for the original construction, as well as plans and specifications for the buildings. The subseries contains architectural drawings for the Lawyers' Club and Dormitory, the Legal Research Building, plot plans for the entire law quadrangle, and reproductions of renderings of the exterior of the law quadrangle. The most extensive collection of drawings are for Hutchins Hall, detailing both interior and exterior construction and finishing.
      - Architectural drawings
        - General
          - Law school buildings
            - Plot plans., undated; 1 drawings pencil on tracing paper; 1 blueprints (Folder Ac)
            - Exterior renderings, undated; 5 photographs (Folder Ac)
          - Lawyers' Club and Dormitory, circa 1924; 1 drawings pencil on tracing paper; 3 blueprints (Folder Ac)
          - Legal Research
            - Interior floor plans from faculty, 3 drawings; 3 drawings pencil on heavy paper (Folder Ac)
            - Exterior elevations and interior floor plans by architects, 9 blueprints (Folder Ac)
        - Hutchins Hall
          - Miscellaneous measured drawings, 1931-1932; 7 blueprints (Folder Ac)
            (Includes schedule of finishes, details, heating and ventilation duplicates)
          - Set of measured drawings of each room, undated; 54 blueprints 8.5" x 11" (Folder Ac)
            (Includes specifications for walls, base, floor, trim, and doors)
          - Set of measured drawings, July-August, 1931; 21 blueprints (Folder Ac)
            (Includes floor plans, heating, ventilation, electrical)
          - Set of measured drawings, August 1930-February 1932; 71 blueprints (Tube 1)
            (Possibly complete set, includes floor plans, elevations, interior and exterior details, lecture and class rooms, fixtures)
      - Budget and Receipts
        - 1923-1924 (Box 65)
        - 1929-1932 (Box 65)
        - Bank Correspondence (Box 65)
        - Hayden Company, 1923-1925 (Box 65)
        - York and Sawyer, 1923-1924 (Box 65)
      - Construction Daily Report, 1930 (Box 65)
      - Contracts, 1923; 1929-1930 (Box 65)
      - Correspondence
        - Marion L. Burton (President), 1922-1924 (Box 65)
        - Hayden Company, 1919-1930; 3 folders (Box 65)
        - Law School Administration, 1921-1938; 6 folders (Box 65)
        - James O. Murfin (Regent), 1927-1930 (Box 65)
        - Walter Sawyer (Regent), 1925-1929 (Box 65)
        - York and Sawyer, 1919-1929; 8 folders (Box 65)
      - Estimates, 1920-1923 (Box 65)
      - Hutchins Hall
        - Correspondence, 1930-1933; 6 folders (Box 65)
        - Furniture and Equipment (Box 66)
        - Preliminary Plans (Box 66)
      - Landscaping, 1924-1925 (Box 66)
      - Law Library, ca., 1927 (Box 66)
      - Lawyers' Club
        - Automobiles (Box 66)
        - Correspondence, 1921-1929; 5 folders (Box 66)
        - Dedication, 1921-1925 (Box 66)
      - Newspaper Clippings (Box 66)
      - Specifications
        - John P. Cook Dormitory, 1929 (Box 66)
        - Hutchins Hall, 1931-1932; 2 folders (Box 66)
        - Lawyers' Club and Dormitory, 1923 (Box 66)
        - Legal Research, 1929; 2 folders (Box 66)
        - Miscellaneous, 1920; 1930 (Box 66)
    - Management
      The subseries of documents relating to the management of the buildings focuses on the Lawyers' Club and law school reorganization. The Lawyers' Club papers include general correspondence about its management, organization, and genesis, as well as the correspondence of Professor Grismore, first secretary of the Lawyers' Club, documenting it as an organization within the law school. The subseries also includes the correspondence of John T. Creighton, William W. Cook's attorney, member of the Lawyers' Club Board of Governors. He frequently served as a liaison for Cook in the management of the gift to the law school and the Lawyers' Club. There is also correspondence and reports that relate to a proposed reorganization of the law school as a result of Mr. Cook's gift to the school.
      - John T. Creighton correspondence, 1922-1926; 9 folders (Box 66)
      - John T. Creighton correspondence, 1927-1928; 2 folders (Box 67)
      - Law School Reorganization, 1929-1930; 2 folders (Box 67)
      - Lawyers' Club
        - General correspondence, 1923-1930; 4 folders (Box 67)
        - Grismore correspondence, 1925-1930; 3 folders (Box 67)
        - Non-Residents, 1925 (Box 67)
        - Organization, 1924 (Box 67)
        - Report, 1929 (Box 67)
  - William W. Cook
    The William W. Cook series of documents contains some personal papers of William W. Cook and papers which relate to his gift to the law school, outside of the construction of the law quadrangle. This subseries includes correspondence and copies of his publications, personal correspondence, the litigation surrounding his estate and his bequest to the university, and financial arrangements concerning additional gifts to the university.
    - Books and Articles
      - American Institutions, revisions (Box 67)
      - "Legal Research,", 1927 (Box 67)
      - Miscellaneous law articles, 1922-1923; 1929 (Box 67)
      - Principles of Corporation Law
        - Correspondence, 1924-1926; 2 folders (Box 67)
        - Reviews (Box 67)
    - Correspondence
      - Harry B. Hutchins, 1920-1930; 2 folders (Box 67)
      - Personal, 1911-1914; 1924-1925; 1930; 3 folders (Box 67)
    - Estate Litigation
      - Briefs, 2 folders (Box 67)
      - Correspondence, 1930-1931; 2 folders (Box 67)
      - Divorce Proceedings (Box 67)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1930 (Box 67)
      - Trust documents, 1923-1924 (Box 67)
      - Will copy and revisions (Box 67)
    - Law Review Trust Fund, 1923-1927 (Box 67)
    - William W. Cook Foundation, 1929-1930 (Box 67)
- Law School Lecture Series
  The Law School Lecture series in document several on-going lecture series sponsored by the Law School including the William W. Cook Lectures on American Institutions and the Thomas M. Cooley Lectures.
  - William W. Cook Lectures on American Institutions, 1941-1993
    The William W. Cook Lectures on American Institutions [1996 Accession] (1.0 linear feet, 1941-1993) document the lecture series named in honor of alumnus William W. Cook (A.B. 1880; LL.B., 1882). A committee was authorized by the Regents in July 1942 to comply with Cook's will which provided an endowment to pay for lectures on American institutions and their preservation, and for the publication of the lectures. Lecturers receive an honorarium and are expected to deliver three to five public lectures resulting in a manuscript suitable for publication. The material in this series contains committee records, 1941-1975, including information on the Cook bequest, and files on Cook lecturers arranged chronologically.
    - General
      The material in this series contains committee records, 1941-1975, including information on the Cook bequest, and files on Cook lecturers arranged chronologically.
      - "A Great Foundation for Legal Studies at the University of Michigan", Undated (Box 76)
        (Typescript re: the Cook endowments)
      - Florentine Cook Heath (niece of W. W. Cook), 1955-1958 (Box 76)
      - W. W. Cook Lectureship Committee, 1941-1975; 3 folders (Box 76)
      - General Correspondence, 1964-1970; 1972-1978; 2 folders (Box 76)
      - Publishing, 1960-1979 (Box 76)
    - Lecturer Files
      The lecturer files typically contain letters of invitation and subsequent negotiations and date from 1965 to 1993. Records relating to arrangements such as publication of the lectures are also present. A few of the files include transcripts and drafts of the lectures. These items have been noted on the inventory.
      - Leslie W. Dunbar, 1965 (Box 76)
      - Gilbert F. White, 1966; 2 folders (Box 76)
        (includes draft manuscript)
      - Francis Keppel, 1967 (Box 76)
      - (no lecturer), 1968 (Box 76)
      - Willard Wirtz, 1969 (Box 76)
      - Daniel J. Boorstin, 1972 (Box 76)
      - Nathan Glazer, 1974 (Box 76)
      - John Rawls (Visiting Professorship), 1974 (Box 76)
      - Richard E. Neustadt, 1976 (Box 76)
        (Includes partial photocopy of lecture)
      - Ada Louise Huxtable, 1977 (Box 76)
      - Sir Peter Medawar, Richard C. Atkinson, Jerome Wiesne, 1978 (Box 76)
        (includes remarks of Medawar and Atkinson)
      - Garry Wills, 1979 (Box 76)
      - Daniel Bell, 1980 (Box 76)
        (includes draft of remarks)
      - Austin Ranney, 1981 (Box 76)
      - Irving Howe, 1983 (Box 76)
      - Peter L. Berger, 1983 (Box 76)
        (includes typescript of lectures)
      - Alice M. Rivlin, 1985 (Box 76)
      - Wallace Stegner, 1986 (Box 76)
      - David Brion Davis, 1987 (Box 76)
      - Bartlett Giamatti, 1989 (Box 76)
      - Sir Geoffrey Rudolf Elton, 1990 (Box 76)
      - Arthur C. Danto, 1991 (Box 76)
      - Stephen Weil, Annamaria Petrioli Tofani, Marcia Tucker, 1993; 3 folders (Box 76)
        (includes manuscripts of lectures)
  - Thomas M. Cooley Lectures
    Thomas M. Cooley Lectures [1996 Accession] (0.75 linear feet, 1969-1993) document the lecture program named in honor of Thomas M. Cooley, a member of the first law faculty at the university in 1859 and subsequent dean. The lectureship was established by the Law School faculty in order to stimulate research and to communicate research through public lectures. The lectureship is supported by the William W. Cook endowment. The files were maintained chronologically by the name of the lecturers and include correspondence with the lecturers, usually distinguished lawyers or scholars. The files also contain news releases, general biographical material, and occasionally, copies or drafts of the text delivered at the lecture. Those files which contain copies or drafts are noted in the inventory.
    - Lecturers
      - General Correspondence, 1961-1975 (Box 77)
      - Philip B. Kur, 1969 (Box 77)
      - Bernard Botien, 1970 (Box 77)
      - Maurice Rosenberg, Benjamin Kaplan, Mauro Cappelletti, 1970 (Box 77)
        (includes draft of Kaplan's lecture)
      - Louis L. Jaffe, 1971 (Box 77)
      - Boris I. Bittker, 1973 (Box 77)
        (includes articles relating to lecture)
      - Norval Morris, 1974 (Box 77)
      - Robert S. Morison, 1975 (Box 77)
        (includes draft of lecture)
      - Stanley M. Katz, Morton J. Horowitz, William E. Nelson, 1975 (Box 77)
      - Jesse H. Choper, 1977 (Box 77)
        (includes article based on lecture)
      - Judge Harold Leventhal, 1978 (Box 77)
      - Robert H. Bork and Norman Dorsen, 1979 (Box 77)
        (includes draft of Dorsen lecture)
      - Guido Calabresi, 1979 (Box 77)
      - Franklin E. Zimring, 1980 (Box 77)
      - Elliot L. Richardson, 1982 (Box 77)
        (includes edited transcript)
      - Paul C. Weiler, Jochen A. Frowhein, Francis G. Jacobs, 1983 (Box 77)
        (includes text of all three lectures)
      - Melvin A. Eisenberg, 1985 (Box 77)
      - R. Kent Greenawalt, 1986 (Box 77)
      - Anthony T. Kronman, 1987 (Box 77)
      - Louis Henkin, 1988 (Box 77)
        (includes lecture text)
      - Richard A. Posner, 1989 (Box 77)
        (includes articles based on lecture)
      - Jon Elster, 1991; 2 folders (Box 77)
      - Robert W. Gordon, 1993 (Box 77)
- Committee of Visitors, 1963-1993
  Committee of Visitors records (3.0 linear feet, 1963-1993), illustrate the work of the alumni body created in 1962 to examine the operation of the Law School and to advise the dean and faculty on issues facing the School. Documentation includes agendas, reports, rosters of committee members, schedules, and correspondence between members of the committee and Law School representatives. During the annual meetings members of the Committee of Visitors attended classes, met with students and faculty, and received reports and briefings on admissions, curriculum, financial aid, minority concerns, and placement. The records are arranged chronologically by meeting.
  - Meeting Files
    - 1963 (Box 78)
    - 1964 (Box 78)
    - 1965, 2 folders (Box 78)
    - 1966, 3 folders (Box 78)
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 78)
    - 1968, 4 folders (Box 78)
    - 1969, 2 folders (Box 78)
    - 1970 (Box 78)
    - 1971 (Box 79)
    - 1972 (Box 79)
    - 1973, 2 folders (Box 79)
    - 1974, 2 folders (Box 79)
    - 1975, 2 folders (Box 79)
    - 1976, 2 folders (Box 79)
    - 1977, 2 folders (Box 79)
    - 1978 (Box 79)
    - 1979 (Box 79)
    - 1980 (Box 79)
    - 1981, 3 folders (Box 79)
    - 1982, 3 folders (Box 79)
    - 1983, 3 folders (Box 79)
    - 1984, 3 folders (Box 79)
    - 1985, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1986, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1987, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1988, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1989, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1990, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1991, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1992, 3 folders (Box 80)
    - 1993, 3 folders (Box 80)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual Materials series contains three series, Photographs, Audiocassettes and Videocassettes.
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries includes faculty and staff portraits, scenes from the Judge Advocate General's School held during World War II, and photographs of the Law Library and Law Quadrangle buildings. There are also student photographs, including scattered class photographs and informal shots; a collection of the holiday cards sent by deans Sandalow and Bollinger featuring images of the Law School; photographs of the Law Library addition while it was under construction; and photographs of Senior Day--the Law School graduation ceremony--including pictures of the speakers and some of the degree recipients.
    - Faculty and Staff
      - Group portraits (Box 68)
        (Also in UBImum C61
      - Individuals A-B (Box 68)
      - Individuals C-F (Box 68)
      - Individuals G-I (Box 68)
      - Individuals J-L (Box 68)
      - Individuals M-O (Box 68)
      - Individuals P-R (Box 68)
      - Individuals S-T (Box 68)
      - Individuals U-Z and unidentified (Box 68)
      - Raw Review Caricatures (Box 68)
    - Judge Advocate General's (JAG) School (World War II)
      - Class portraits (Box 68)
      - Classrooms, recreation, etc (Box 68)
      - Field exercises (Box 68)
      - Drills and formations-Ferry Field (Box 68)
      - Drills and formations-Law quadrangle (Box 68)
      - Parades (Box 68)
      - Staff-Group portraits (Box 68)
      - Staff-Individuals (Box 68)
    - Law Library
      - Addition (1980)-Drawings and model (Box 68)
        (also 1 photo in Bimu/C61, outsize)
      - Staff (Box 68)
      - Views (Box 68)
    - Law Quadrangle buildings
      - Architectural ornaments (Box 68)
      - Views showing construction, 1923-1924; 3 envelopes; 1 volumes (Box 68)
      - Drawings of stained glass windows (Folder BImu C61)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 68)
        (includes color transparencies)
    - Students
      - Classroom scenes (Box 68)
      - Group portraits (Box 68)
      - Law Quadrangle scenes (Box 68)
      - Legal Aid Clinic (Box 68)
      - Reunions (Box 68)
      - Miscellaneous student activities (Box 68)
        (including Dominick's Restaurant)
    - Composite Class Photos, 1873-1966
      The Composite Class Photos consist of negatives, copy prints and digital scans of graduating class photos. The originals of many of the photos are at the Law School. The scanned images are also available online through the Bentley Library Image Bank.
      - Negatives (Box 68)
        (4x5 copy negatives of original prints at the Law School)
        (missing years 1874, 1876-1878 1883, 1885, 1887, 1888, 1908-1910, 1959, 1965)
      - Prints
        (16x20 copy prints made from scanned 4x5 negatives, all in BImu C61)
        - 1873-1907 (Folder 1)
        - 1911-1935 (Folder 2)
        - 1936-1966 (Folder 3)
      - Digital files, 86 digital files on 3 CDs (Box 3)
        (tiff format scans made from copy negatives, also includes scans for 1877, 1883, 1885-1888, 1908-1910 from originals at BHL)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Television system-Law School and Circuit Court (Box 68)
      - Visiting dignitaries and University of Michigan officials (Box 68)
        (including Dean Acheson)
      - Christmas Cards (Law School exteriors; includes one negative and one color separation), 1981-1993; undated (Box 117)
      - Construction of Law Library Addition, circa 1980 (Box 117)
      - Directory Photographs
        - Class of 1975, circa 1972 (Box 117)
          (identified)
        - C.1970s (identified) (Box 117)
        - 1978 Summer Starters, 1978 (Box 117)
          (negatives; identified)
      - Faculty Photograph, Fall 1969 (Box 117)
      - Law School Exteriors, undated (Box 117)
      - Law School Logo (from International Alumni Reunion), circa 1991 (Box 117)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 117)
        (Law Quad tree transplantation c.1920s, 1975 Campbell Competition, and Lee Bollinger portrait)
      - Senior Day Speakers and Degree Recipients
        - 1968 (Box 117)
        - (Harry Edwards, speaker), December 1979 (Box 117)
        - 1983, 1986 (Box 117)
        - 1988-1991 (Box 117)
        - 1993 (Box 117)
  - Audiocassettes
    Audiocassettes contains seven tapes, including one of Antigone's Reply, a work for voice and piano by William Albright of the School of Music commissioned by the Law School (see also the William Albright Papers at the Bentley Historical Library) and tapes of two Cook lectures, in 1993 and 1995.
    - Antigone's Reply, written by William Albright, performed by Judi Lamble and Thomas Keyce, Bruce Patterson, pianist, December 4, 1987 (Box 118)
    - Cook Lecture #2, by Annamaria Petrioli Tofani, April 15, 1993 (Box 118)
    - Cook Lecture: "U.S. Foreign Policy and the Global Economy," by Professor Jeffrey Sachs, January 17, 18 and 19, 1995; 4 audiocassettes (Box 118)
    - "A Tribute to Wade H. McCree, Jr., Presented by the University of Michigan Law School Fund," compiled and narrated by Mary Talen, 1989 (Box 118)
  - Videocassettes